<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Ben Hoen</origin>
				<origin>James Diffendorfer</origin>
				<origin>Joseph Rand</origin>
				<origin>Louisa Kramer</origin>
				<origin>Christopher Garrity</origin>
				<origin>Hannah Hunt</origin>
				<pubdate>20180710</pubdate>
				<title>United States Wind Turbine Database (1.1)</title>
				<geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)and CSV file</geoform>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
					<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<onlink>https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb/</onlink>
				<onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7TX3DN0</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This dataset provides locations and technical specifications of wind turbines in the United States, almost all of which are utility-scale. Utility-scale turbines are ones that generate power and feed it into the grid, supplying a utility with energy. They are usually much larger than turbines that would feed a homeowner or business. The regularly updated database has wind turbine records that have been collected, digitized, and locationally verified. Turbine data were gathered from the Federal Aviation Administration's (FAA) Digital Obstacle File (DOF) and Obstruction Evaluation Airport Airspace Analysis (OE-AAA), the American Wind Energy Association (AWEA), Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL), and the United States Geological Survey (USGS), and were merged and collapsed into a single data set. Verification of the turbine positions was done by visual interpretation using high-resolution aerial imagery in ESRI ArcGIS Desktop. A locational error of plus or minus 10 meters for turbine locations was tolerated. Technical specifications for turbines were assigned based on the wind turbine make and models as provided by manufacturers and project developers directly, and via FAA datasets, information on the wind project developer or turbine manufacturer websites, or other online sources. Some facility and turbine information on make and model did not exist or was difficult to obtain. Thus, uncertainty may exist for certain turbine specifications. Similarly, some turbines were not yet built, not built at all, or for other reasons cannot be verified visually. Location and turbine specifications data quality are rated and a confidence is recorded for both. None of the data are field verified.</abstract>
			<purpose>The purpose of this information is to provide a regularly updated, publicly available, spatially referenced, national dataset made up almost entirely of utility-scale wind turbine locations and their technical specifications. An appropriate use of the data would be for scientific analysis, research or for general interest for the public. Identification of turbines that have been retrofitted, repowered, decommissioned, and/or removed is a continual ongoing effort; thus, the dataset may contain turbines that were previously verified and subsequently removed.</purpose>
			<supplinf>Some facility and turbine information on make and model did not exist or was difficult to obtain. Thus, uncertainty may exist for certain turbine specifications. Similarly, some turbines were not yet built, not built at all, or for other reasons cannot be verified visually. Location and turbine specifications data quality are rated and a confidence is recorded for both. None of the data are field verified.</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>19810101</begdate>
					<enddate>20180422</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>ground condition</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Planned</progress>
			<update>Unknown</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-171.71307373</westbc>
				<eastbc>144.72265625</eastbc>
				<northbc>66.8399047852</northbc>
				<southbc>13.3893814087</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>None</themekt>
				<themekey>turbine</themekey>
				<themekey>energy</themekey>
				<themekey>shapefile</themekey>
				<themekey>renewable</themekey>
				<themekey>wind turbine</themekey>
				<themekey>wind farm</themekey>
				<themekey>wind facility</themekey>
				<themekey>database</themekey>
				<themekey>turbine characteristics</themekey>
				<themekey>verified</themekey>
				<themekey>USWTDB</themekey>
				<themekey>national</themekey>
				<themekey>ngmdb</themekey>
				<themekey>wind</themekey>
				<themekey>USGS</themekey>
				<themekey>LBNL</themekey>
				<themekey>AWEA</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>None</placekt>
				<placekey>United States</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>None</accconst>
		<useconst>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</cntorg>
					<cntper>Ben Hoen</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Research Scientist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
					<address>20 Sawmill Road</address>
					<city>Milan</city>
					<state>NY</state>
					<postal>12571</postal>
					<country>United States</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>845-758-1896</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>510-486-6996</cntfax>
				<cntemail>bhoen@lbl.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>Credit to cooperative agreement and collaboration between the U.S. Geological Survey, the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, and the American Wind Energy Association to compile and release these data.</datacred>
		<native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft [Unknown] Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>Turbine data points were spatially verified in aerial imagery to confirm or edit their correct position. The map scale used while verifying and digitizing turbines depended on location, need, and imagery availability. Authors used aerial imagery with a typical assessment map scale of 1:2,000 to 1:5,000, none of the spatial verification was done at a map scale smaller than 1:5,000. Uncertainty may exist for certain turbine locations as indicated in confidence turbine location field (t_conf_loc). Uncertainty in turbine specifications was indicated in the confidence of attribute field (t_conf_atr).</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
		<complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. It is regularly updated and turbines will be added and removed over time, and characteristics might be altered over time as well. Users should be aware that the location data was based on a snapshot of time; turbines could have been removed after that time or built since the image date. None of the data are field verified.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>The wind turbine points were horizontally verified with aerial imagery as specified in the image source attribute. NAIP provides 1 meters ground sample distance orthoimagery to within plus or minus 6 meters to true ground at a 95-percent confidence level. The Bing Maps Aerial basemaps and Digital Globe imagery have a variable resolution and accuracy based on image source, type, and location. The Bing Maps Aerial basemaps horizontal accuracy for CONUS is estimated to be 0.3m to 0.03m. Digital Globe imagery is estimated to be 0.3m to 0.03m.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>FAA</origin>
						<pubdate>20180424</pubdate>
						<title>Digital Obstacle File</title>
						<geoform>Other</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Aeronautical Information Services</pubplace>
							<publish>FAA</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>https://www.faa.gov/air_traffic/flight_info/aeronav/digital_products/dof/</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate> 20180226</begdate>
							<enddate>20180422</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>FAA DOF</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
						<pubdate>201505</pubdate>
						<title>Onshore Industrial Wind Turbine Locations for the United States to March 2014</title>
						<geoform>Vector Digital Data Set</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</pubplace>
							<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7251G8Q</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>19810101</begdate>
							<enddate>20140302</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>USGS 2014 Wind Turbine Locations</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>American Wind Energy Association</origin>
						<pubdate>20180425</pubdate>
						<title>WindIQ</title>
						<geoform>Other</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Available to AWEA members only</pubplace>
							<publish>AWEA</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>https://www.awea.org/windiq</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>19810101</begdate>
							<enddate>20180331</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>AWEA WindIQ</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set. Data is only for internal AWEA member use.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</origin>
						<pubdate>unknown</pubdate>
						<title>LBNL Wind Turbine Database</title>
						<geoform>Other</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>NOT APPLICABLE - LBNL internal data</pubplace>
							<publish>LBNL</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>NOT APPLICABLE</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>19860101</begdate>
							<enddate>20161231</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>LBNL WTDB</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set. Data is only for internal use.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>FAA</origin>
						<pubdate>20180421</pubdate>
						<title>Obstruction Evaluation Airport Airspace Analysis</title>
						<geoform>Other</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Obstruction Evaluation Group</pubplace>
							<publish>FAA</publish>
						</pubinfo>
						<onlink>https://oeaaa.faa.gov/oeaaa/external/public/publicAction.jsp?action=showCaseDownloadForm</onlink>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>20000829</begdate>
							<enddate>20180402</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>FAA OE-AAA</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Source information used in support of the development of the data set.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Prior to steps listed below, US wind turbines were identified, mapped, and verified by USGS for a separate dataset: "Onshore Industrial Wind Turbine Locations for the United States to March 2014". A description of the process to develop that dataset can be found in the metadata file for that release (https://doi.org/10.5066/F7251G8Q). Building off this earlier effort, the following steps were taken to expand and update the United States Wind Turbine Database (USWTDB) with the collaboration between USGS, LBNL, and AWEA. Please note that some steps are iterated on a quarterly basis to keep the dataset current. (1) The March 2014 USGS dataset 48,956 turbines, 34,864 of which had unique FAA Obstacle Repository System (ORS) numbers was merged with (2) the LBNL wind turbine dataset. It had previously existed separately in house, and also had the FAA ORS number as well as many of the same fields as the USGS dataset. It was merged into the USGS dataset using the ORS number, bringing in LBNL fields and IDs. (3) Non-matching LBNL turbines were also added as LBNL only turbines. (4) The most recent FAA Digital Obstacle File (DOF) was downloaded and filtered for "windmills", and reprojected from WGS-84, as FAA provided it, to NAD-83 datum, the USGS and LBNL datum. These new coordinates were used later in the process. (5) The DOF dataset was then merged into the working USWTDB using ORS number, keeping new (non-matching) DOF Only turbines, and DOF variables (faa_aglht, faa_amslht, faa_asn, ylat, xlong). (6) The most recent FAA Obstacle Evaluation Airport Airspace Analysis (OE-AAA) file was downloaded and filtered for "windmills". (7) The OE-AAA dataset was merged into working USWTDB using Aeronautical Study Number (ASN) and preserved as the faa_asn attribute,keeping new (non-matching) turbines as OE only and OE-AAA variables (oe_builtdate, oe_appdate, oe_expdate, oe_comdate, notice of, status, dtrmntn, oe_aglht, ylat, xlong). (8) The latest AWEA WindIQ turbine dataset was downloaded. (9) A geospatial match between AWEA turbines and working USWTDB was performed using "geonear" command in Stata statistical analysis software and the following steps: [a] Save separate AWEA and working USWTDB datasets. [b] Run "geonear" command in Stata between the two datasets to determine and "match" nearest neighbors (i.e., these turbines are suspected to be the same turbine but from the two different datasets), and calculate the distance between them. [c] Calculate differences in installed year, hub height, rotor diameter, and total height between "matched" turbine pairs. [d] Accept "match" (meaning assume they are, in fact, the same turbine) IF distance between pairs is zero (perfect geospatial match), OR distance between pairs is less than 100 feet (30.5 m) AND hub height, rotor diameter, and installed year are equal between the pairs. If the match criteria were not met, both turbines in the pair were saved for subsequent visual inspection and "manual" confirmation of match. Non-matching AWEA turbines are added to the dataset as AWEA-only turbines and all AWEA variables (turbine ID, p_year, t_cap, t_hh, t_rd, t_tth, ylat, xlong, t_manu, t_model, t_state, as well as other variables) were added to the dataset. (10) A hierarchy was developed because multiple datasets contain some of the same fields (e.g., t_ttlh was contained in USGS, LBNL, DOF, OE-AAA and AWEA datasets)Because LBNL and AWEA data are sourced from two high-quality sources (OEMs and developers) and reconciled to eliminate differences, LBNL data is the primary source for turbine attributes and turbine project characteristics, then AWEA, USGS, DOF, and finally OE-AAA. In the overwhelming majority of cases, differences between sources were minimal, but when discrepancies existed that order was used to populate fields. All fields that are missing from higher-order sources are populated from lower sources. (11) The working (i.e., fully merged) USWTDB was spatially joined with base layers via ArcMap in order to pin t_state, t_county and t_fips to turbine points. (12) Turbine points were selected by state, saved as an individual turbine file for each state, and distributed to authors for editing. (13) A basemap image from Digital Globe was added to the ArcMap project file. If Digital Globe imagery did not show a turbine installation, USDA/NAIP County Mosaic Orthoimagery Google Earth imagery was cross checked. Previous bing map image source was retained for some of the previous USGS data. (14) Turbine points were visually verified and edited/moved to the base of the turbine as needed with an estimated tolerance of 10 meters. (15) If the turbine data point was not seen on an image, the t_conf_loc was entered as 1. If the turbine point was in partial construction or with other doubts, the t_conf_loc was entered as 2. If a turbine was clearly seen on image, the t_conf_loc was entered as 3. Turbines that have not yet been visually verified are labeled with 0 in t_conf_loc. (16) Turbine points that had existed previously but were since decommissioned and removed were flagged as decommissioned and later removed( see step 20). (17) Duplicate turbine points (largely resulting from AWEA geospatial merge) were identified and t_img_date, and t_img_srce were attributed for each turbine. (18) Non-turbine points that had been assigned FAA Obstacle Repository System (ORS) numbers or were digitized in the process such as communications towers, meteorological towers, water windmills, power transmission towers, etc., were removed. (19) Edited wind turbine files for each state were merged into one single shapefile, turbines identified as duplicates were matched, all fields were collapsed into a single turbine observation, and duplicate points were removed. (20) Turbines flagged as decommissioned were removed. (21) QA/QC was conducted for spatial accuracy and attribution by a peer or a supervisor other than the author that initially completed the work. As noted above, steps 4-21 are repeated on a quarterly basis, using the most recent USWTDB as the starting point. </procdesc>
				<procdate>20180702</procdate>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Point</direct>
		<ptvctinf>
			<sdtsterm>
				<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt>57646</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
		</ptvctinf>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<geograph>
				<latres>0.0197478977</latres>
				<longres>0.0257014134</longres>
				<geogunit>Decimal Degrees</geogunit>
			</geograph>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn>
				<ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
				<enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
				<enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
			</enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>case_id</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>unique stable identification number</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>3000001</rdommin>
						<rdommax>3086016</rdommax>
						<attrunit>1</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>faa_ors</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>faa unique identifier for each turbine for cross-reference to the faa digital obstacle files (faa dof )</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>FAA, https://www.faa.gov/air_traffic/flight_info/aeronav/digital_products/dof/</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>identifier with the first two digits indicating a state, then a dash, with a sequential number following; "missing" records are ones with no known DOF number</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>faa_asn</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>faa obstruction evaluation airport airspace analysis (oe-aaa) aeronautical study number (asn)</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>FAA, https://oeaaa.faa.gov/oeaaa/external/public/publicAction.jsp</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>year-region-number-case type (faa regional boundaries id across the country such as: AAL, ACE, AEA, AGL, ANE, ANM, ASO, ASW, AWP, WTE and WTW) (case types: Nonrule Making Airport. (NRA), Nonrule (NR), or an Obstruction Evaluation (OE) study; "missing" records are those with no known asn number</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>usgs_pr_id</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>unique, stable object number for cross-reference</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>USGS https://doi.org/10.5066/F7251G8Q</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>unique, stable object number for cross-reference to the USGS Onshore Industrial Wind Turbine Locations for the United States 2013 and 2014 products; -9999 values were not part of the referenced dataset, from the USGS https://doi.org/10.5066/F7251G8Q</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_state</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>state where turbine is located</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>U.S Census https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/cbf/cbf_state.html</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>2 letter standard state postal abbreviation, based on spatial join of turbine points with US state and county shapefile</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_county</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>county or county equivalent where turbine is located</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>U.S Census https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/cbf/cbf_counties.html</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>County or county equivalent, based on spatial join of turbine points with US state and county shapefile</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_fips</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>state and county fips where turbine is located, based on spatial join of turbine points with US state and county shapefile.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>U.S. Census</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<codesetd>
						<codesetn>FIPS Code (5-Digit State &amp; County ID)</codesetn>
						<codesets>FIPS / ANSI (http://www.itl.nist.gov/fipspubs/co-codes/states.txt)</codesets>
					</codesetd>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>p_name</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>name of the wind power project that the turbine is a part of</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Project names are typically provided to AWEA by the developer; some names are identified from other internet resources, and others are created by the authors to differentiate them from previous projects. If no project name can be identified via these methods, authors assigned one based on the county where the turbines are located.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>p_year</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Year the wind power project became operational and began providing power. In some cases, the year is estimated based on the year the turbine was erected, which will precede when it became operational, and sometimes fall in the preceding year; -9999 values are unknown.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>1981</rdommin>
						<rdommax>2018</rdommax>
						<attrunit>Year</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>p_tnum</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>number of turbines in the wind power project</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>1</rdommin>
						<rdommax>1832</rdommax>
						<attrunit>Count</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>p_cap</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>cumulative capacity of all turbines in the wind power project, in megawatts (MW); -9999 values are unknown</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>0.05</rdommin>
						<rdommax>495.01</rdommax>
						<attrunit>Megawatts</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_manu</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>turbine manufacturer - name of the original equipment manufacturer of the turbine</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>E.g., Vestas, Siemens, Suzlon, etc.; "missing" values are unknown</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_model</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>turbine model - manufacturer's model name of each turbine</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>E.g., 1.5SLE, V100_1.8, Z50, etc.; "missing" values are unknown</udom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_cap</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Turbine rated capacity in kilowatt (kW). The manufacturer's stated output power at rated wind speed. Data from AWEA, manufacturer data, and/or other internet resources; -9999 values are unknown values are unknown</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>40</rdommin>
						<rdommax>6000</rdommax>
						<attrunit>kilowatt</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_hh</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>turbine hub height in meters (m). Data from AWEA, manufacturer data, and/or other internet resources; -9999 values are unknown</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>18.2</rdommin>
						<rdommax>116.5</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_rd</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>turbine rotor diameter in meters (m); -9999 values are unknown</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>11</rdommin>
						<rdommax>150</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_rsa</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>turbine rotor swept area square meters (m^2); -9999 values are unknown, calculated as 3.14159 (([rotor_dia] /2)*([rotor_dia] /2)</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>95.03</rdommin>
						<rdommax>17671.46</rdommax>
						<attrunit>square meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_ttlh</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>turbine total height - height of entire wind turbine from ground to tip of a vertically extended blade above the tower. Computed as the hub height plus half of the rotor diameter, in meters, when t_hh and t_rd are non-missing. Otherwise, the total height as provided by the FAA DOF or FAA OE/AAA is used, which can be considered a maximum height; -9999 values are unknown</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>9.1</rdommin>
						<rdommax>200.3</rdommax>
						<attrunit>meter</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_conf_atr</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Level of confidence in the turbine's attributes, from low to high</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>0</edomv>
						<edomvd>attribute confidence has not been assigned for this turbine</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>1</edomv>
						<edomvd>no confidence: no information found</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>2</edomv>
						<edomvd>partial confidence: incomplete information or discrepancies across data sources or other issues found</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>3</edomv>
						<edomvd>Definition: full confidence: consistent information across multiple data sources</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_conf_loc</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Level of confidence in turbine location, from low to high</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>1</edomv>
						<edomvd>no confidence: nothing on image, image has clouds, never built, previously removed, needs newer imagery</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>2</edomv>
						<edomvd>partial confidence: image shows developed pad with base and/or turbine parts on ground</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>3</edomv>
						<edomvd>ull confidence: image shows an installed turbine or tower being constructed, the tower is least partially present with neighboring turbine constructed</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_img_date</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>date of image used to visually verify turbine location (note if NAIP is the image source the month and day were set to 01/01)</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>5/22/2002</rdommin>
						<rdommax>10/18/2018</rdommax>
						<attrunit>date</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>t_img_srce</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>source of image used to visually verify turbine location</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>Bing Maps Aerial</edomv>
						<edomvd>ESRI ArcMap Base maps, available from ESRI ArcMap</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>Digital Globe</edomv>
						<edomvd>Digital Globe EV WebHosting Imagery from evwhs.digitalglobe.com</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>Google Earth</edomv>
						<edomvd>Google Earth</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>missing</edomv>
						<edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>NAIP</edomv>
						<edomvd>National Agriculture Imagery Program County Mosaics from https://datagateway.nrcs.usda.gov/</edomvd>
						<edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>xlong</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>current longitude of the turbine point, in decimal degrees calculated in Arc Map using GCS: North American 1983 (NAD 83)</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>-171.713074</rdommin>
						<rdommax>144.722656</rdommax>
						<attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>ylat</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>current latitude of the turbine point, in decimal degrees calculated in Arc Map using GCS: North American 1983 (NAD 83)</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<rdom>
						<rdommin>13.389381</rdommin>
						<rdommax>66.839905</rdommax>
						<attrunit>decimal degrees</attrunit>
					</rdom>
				</attrdomv>
			</attr>
		</detailed>
		<overview>
			<eaover>None</eaover>
			<eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
					<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>CO</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
					<country>United States</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
		<distliab>Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Geological Survey. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items for other than personal use must be secured from the copyright owner. This database has been approved for release and publication by the Director of the USGS. Although this database has been subjected to rigorous review and is substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, it is released on condition that neither the USGS nor the United States Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from its authorized or unauthorized use. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. While these data are believed to contain correct information, neither the United States Government nor any agency thereof, nor The Regents of the University of California, nor any of their employees, makes any warranty, express or implied, or assumes any legal responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, or represents that its use would not infringe privately owned rights. Reference herein to any specific commercial product, process, or service by its trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise, does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United States Government or any agency thereof, or The Regents of the University of California.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Point) and CSV file</formname>
				</digtinfo>
				<digtopt>
					<onlinopt>
						<computer>
							<networka>
								<networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7TX3DN0</networkr>
								<networkr>https://eerscmap.usgs.gov/uswtdb</networkr>
							</networka>
						</computer>
					</onlinopt>
				</digtopt>
			</digform>
			<fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
		</stdorder>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20180702</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>James E Diffendorfer</cntper>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Southwest Region</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Research Ecologist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
					<address>Mail Stop 980, W 6th Ave Kipling St</address>
					<city>Lakewood</city>
					<state>CO</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
					<country>United States</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>303-236-5369</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>303-236-5349</cntfax>
				<cntemail>jdiffendorfer@usgs.gov and GS-USWTDB@usgs.gov </cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
	</metainfo>
	<Esri>
		<CreaDate>20180710</CreaDate>
		<CreaTime>09325800</CreaTime>
		<ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat>
		<SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
	</Esri>
</metadata>
